hello welcome back we're here with real
Bradley Lisa and recorded Stefan Bowman
there will be a pre-recorded talk with
some discussion too so thanks all and
looking forward to the talk go for
it
okay
see okay this coming through yes hey
wonderful well then um yeah welcome
everyone uh to my presentation about
neurodes
um my name is Jeff bman I'm a senior
research fellow uh in at University of
Queensland in Australia and sorry I
can't be there live but the time zones
are just too difficult um I want to
start with why we build neurodes and
then introduce what it is but we saw a
couple of challenges and open
signs and one of them is really
non-reproducible workflows so we have um
different great tools uh they run on
lots of different data sets but the
challenge is that if under Ling
dependencies change they produce
slightly different results and that's
really not great if we want to infer
anything on this
data the other challeng that we saw is
infrastructure disparities so lots of
people have access to different Computer
Resources so be their own notebook their
HBC cluster or their cloud provider to
process their data and wherever they
want to run data analysis they need to
come and install their software again
and the software Wills be different
across these installations and it often
costs a lot of time again produces
different results but also costs a lot
of time in maintaining these different
installations the other challenge that
we see is data management so when you
acquire experimental data then from an
MRI scanner for example or behavioral
data then we have to organize it some
sense and that lots of different tools
but we wanted to see if we can make that
a lot easier and then also data storage
and privacy so where we store this data
how we collaborate with others how can
we make this data openly available to
others these are really questions that
we had and thought well can we somehow
make this nice and um nicer for people
and easier to
use so why is it so difficult um in the
end all the software that they use for
neuroimaging analysis
are are software pieces that depend on
other software pieces and these we often
call libraries and what they do is these
libraries
provide functionality that you don't
want to reimplement for example it's you
have your software here that does some
brain Imaging analysis and then you
don't want to reinvent how windows are
drawn on a computer or how data how data
is plotted or how images are processed
so you want to use what other people
have already built to do these
functionalities and then what happens is
your software starts depending on these
because you're using functionality from
these and this usually works quite well
and the reason is that we have in Linux
for example we have package managers
like app yam or if you use Python for
your work you have cona and pip but
pretty much all languages systems have
some kind of package management system
that keep the pendencies compatible with
each other and that's really how it
looks like it's like a puzzle piece
where if one thing upgrades another
thing has to upgrade as well they have
to have matching versions and then uh
we're hoping that this all
works the challenge is with a lot of the
scientific software that we work with
it's often build by scientists who don't
have lot of time they're not really
software Engineers a lot of the time so
what happens is they have unpackaged
scientific software so these scientific
software packages are not available in
standard package systems and that means
that if the operating system upgrades
the package manager doesn't know about
this software because it's un registered
there and then what happens is the
package manager changes something and
because it didn't know about the
software then it breaks and that's
happens unfortunately quite often with
scientific software and at leads to two
problems uh again here's our
reproducibility problem because if we
just depend it on a library and even if
it doesn't break let's say it just
changes functionality our results will
be different and that's really bad for
reproducibility and also this means
portability because if our software is
tightly integrated with the system it
means we can't install software on our
notebook and then run exactly the same
software on an high performance
Computing system because that will have
slightly different dependencies so we
need to install it again often compile
it from source code which can be a
really lot of
work so just to show this reil problem
in a little bit more detail um this is a
great article that looked at software
that depends on gipc gipc is a very
fundamental Linux library and what they
did is they varied only that Library
version um and they left the main piece
of the software intact so they used free
Surfer and lots of other pieces but I'll
Focus here on free Surfer um so it's the
same software installation just in
different operating system just in
different Linux versions in the end and
what happened is in gilp C uh the
exponential function for example was
altered and was made more efficient but
unfortunately this meant that the
Precision of this function changed so
now you you would think that this
doesn't matter right it's like very uh a
couple digits after um uh so yeah so it
should be quite insignificant
unfortunately it's not because free in
particular has a it's a long running
pipeline where we segment the human
brain and this means that if you have
small changes this accumulates over
thousands of processing steps so this
means in the end here they found
differences in millimeter up to .2
millimeter in the cortex
where um this is a change that's only
based on a software version of this
underlying GC so free was identical the
only thing that changed was the
operating system and the thing is this
this was even statistically significant
in some areas and that's really not what
we want because if you acquire patient
data on one software version and then
you have matched controls on another
software version then that would really
lead to significant results that are
actually meaningless because they're
just based on computational
noise so the organic Sol solution that
I've seen in my career is that we just
have people set up different computers
and don't touch them don't try to update
them because people are aware of these
problems
and this is not great because it's not a
great use of resources and also it means
we can't easily take our software and
run it in different computers and this
is this portability problem where let's
say you want to run the same software on
your notebook on your lab workstation in
a secure environment on a cloud provider
on a high performance Computing cluster
or even on the instrument where you're
acquiring your data like your MRIs you
can't just easily uh build an algorithm
on your notebook and then run it on the
MRI scanner it's currently not possible
and but it would be cool right for for
translational studies in patients it
would be fantastic if you had a model um
that you build on your notebook you
validate on lots of data and then uh you
can actually deploy it in in real
clinical environments that would be
fantastic so this is really the problems
that we're trying to solve with this
problem with this project and we adopted
one solution for this which is called
software containers so I quickly want to
introduce what software containers are
and how they work because our software
is based Bas on all of this so software
containers if you've never heard of them
a very simple thought pattern is um
they're just boxes they're boxes to put
software in and they're really like the
stuff where you put food in and put it
in your fridge it's fantastic because it
keeps things separated and you can move
them easily they're very portable and
they don't depend on each
other and that's really what software
containers do they use specific Linux
kernel features called namespaces and c
groups they isolate processes and
dependencies from each other so this
means we can put everything our software
needs into a standardized box and we can
move that across operating
systems and what it basically changes
from our mental model when I said
earlier we have this Lego piece where
this this piece depends tightly on the
other things in the system this now
changes to where we take these
dependencies we put them into the same
box so now we actually don't have a
dependency on the system anymore um the
Box got a bit bigger because we have
these dependencies now included but in
the end stop is cheap but experiments
scientific experiments are expensive so
this is a very low price to pay for a
lot of great features and the whole
Cloud world everything the internet
depends on today is based on software
containers so this is really a very
mature standard that has been adopted
everywhere in the Computing industry so
in science we're just we should just do
it as well um so what we can do we can
package all of our software in these
boxes and then because we have these
standardized interfaces now we can run
this on Windows uh Linux and Mac on
Linux this is a standard kernel feature
so no performance penalties very easy to
run on Mac and Linux we have some
virtualization technology that we need
but that got really good over the last
years so you will not feel that it's
slow it still feels very native but
there is some virtualization there is
some overhead but it's tiny compared to
what we had a couple years
ago so then let's come to what we built
um before I show what we've built in
eurodesk is I want to acknowledge all
the people working on this project
because yes I'm giving the talk here
today but I'm just just one of many
contributors um we started this project
really during Co because we were all
bored and sitting at home and we said
well let's let's solve that problem why
not right we have time um so we got
together couple people all highlighted
in in in bold here and said okay let's
buil this we built a prototype during
hackathon at the obbm and we got funding
from the aidc to build a bigger version
of this and then yeah we got lots of
people involved um slide change sorry um
we got lots of people involved from
involved from across the world and lots
more supporters like the big cloud
providers AWS uh Google had supported us
in the past as well um and then also
the uh the university Cloud providers uh
like egi Jetstream uh ADC nectar Cloud
so that helps a lot and yeah we're
currently funded by the mark Chan
Zuckerberg initiative and welcome trust
to build that uh system out further over
the next
years so this is what we buildt so I'll
start here at the container level so
this is really the software containers
that I introduced earlier where we build
a software container for every piece of
software that people want in this so
here we have a couple of Neuro Imaging
pieces so FM free Surfer field trip ends
and then we can control everything in
there from the binaries the libraries
that we have in there up to the actual
software that people want in the end
like m& which then depends on python
which then depends on cona and so on so
we can control all of these dependencies
and then if you've used the software
container before they are fantastic but
they're not always easy to use like you
have to run specific commands like
Docker run or if you're on an HBC you
need to run Singularity or obtainer run
and we didn't want that people have to
think about this and we build an
accessibility layer we call it but in
the end it's just an abstraction across
multiple container technologies that we
use and it's also a way how we can
stream containers to end users so people
don't have to download these containers
so this this little block here was
actually the most of the work that we
spend on how do we get these containers
to end users and how do we make it easy
for people to use that so but ultimately
what this allows us now to do is we can
run these containers on any system so we
can run this on Mac OS on Linux on the
cloud on Windows on high performance
Computing clusters in Jupiter notebooks
like Google collab on the terminal
pretty much anywhere and we try to
indicate this here with this little
script that goes between systems and
that's not the thing that wasn't
possible before we can code up an
analysis on our notebook and we can move
it across all these systems and will
perform identically and behave
identically across all of these systems
so this really is fantastic for
collaboration for transl of of results
and um for reproducibility in
general and then the community uses that
interacts with the system but also finds
problems bugs and then reports back and
contributes new containers new things
that people want to use in the
system and that's really the ecosystem
that we've
built so the best way to get started
with neurodes is go to our website
neurodes
which runs on the cloud or if you want
to run a local version which runs on
your computer and it depends on your use
case if you have data patient data you
definitely want to run this locally if
you have open data you can use a hosted
version and you're fine and then we have
a more fine grain table down here where
you can select what your compute
platform is what your operating system
is what the interface is that you use
and then you get guided to the
documentation where we guide you through
how to run this on your system
so in the end what you're getting is
you're getting a virtual desktop which
is just a Linux desktop with all the
tools installed and the cool thing is
all the software is ready to go so you
don't need to install anything
everything is there um we have no
dependency issues so we can even have
the same software in different versions
so for example free server is almost
impossible to install different versions
of that software on your computer
because it will replace dependencies
that that other pieces depend on but
because we we wrap all these
dependencies in a software container we
can actually provide all versions of
neurodes of free Surfer for example
going back over the last years without
any problem because of this
containerization the analysis
reproducible uh down to the software
level we're not reproducing anything
Hardware effects I can show this later
but yeah if there's like a CPU
difference between Intel and AMD or arm
we we don't control that but down to the
software level it's reproducible and
then this whole uh system is only 1.5
Gaby in size and the reason is we can
stream all the software we need on
demand in there so when you actually
click on a software it is streamed live
to this endpoint you can also choose to
download it but then we realized
we look at brain Imaging data and and
check if things worked or didn't
work then also we wanted to support high
performance Computing systems so high
performance Computing systems they don't
often come with a desktop interface so
you need to work from the command line
so we build everything to integrate with
these HPC systems so you can easily run
neur desk on there often you can't
install things on there so we took care
of making that possible so you you don't
need any elevated privileges if you have
Singularity or obtainer already
installed on your
HPC and then we also support Jupiter uh
and notebooks computational notebooks in
general because we think this is a great
way of documenting and anal analysis
experimenting collaborating with other
people and sharing results in the end so
we really build it into Jupiter lab as
well and provide with this uh a very
nice interface to people that they
already used to that I know how to work
with then it's also very easy to
contribute new software to it it's all
automated on GitHub so we have GitHub
actions where people can propose a
recipe for a software this gets an
automatically built tested and
integrated into this whole system and
made
available and then we have a system
which is called cvmfs this the streaming
of software that I mentioned it's
developed at CERN so CERN used cvmfs to
stream software and instrument data
across the world and we use exactly the
same system and also collaborate with
the people who run these servers so we
have a primary server where we ingest
all the software and then we distribute
it worldwide so wherever you are in the
world you should get a quick access to
this software and um there's a client in
there that localizes where you are and
gives you the closest server and even if
a server is down it just goes to the
next server so it should be a quite
Reliant system and we're using this
since a couple of years and have never
had any issues with that
and then for the end user it just
appears magically there they just see
the software there and when they start
it it just magically works it's just on
the first start it's a little bit slower
because it has to download certain
things but then on the second start it's
CED locally and it's it behaves like it
was installed
locally so the update in the community
is pretty impressive and we saw really
big growth over the last years so we
have more than a thousand monthly users
on our systems uh they come from over 60
countries so really worldwide adoption
we see that more than 16,000 people
downloaded our main software container
that provides a lot of these things it's
used in university courses for teaching
it's used in conference workshops
because it's fantastic for standardizing
teaching material because you can't you
don't have the problem that students
have different software requirements on
their computers they all log in into
either a cloud-based system or they
install our software container and then
they can run all the same analysis which
is
fantastic and we also have various
collaboration models that we support
with this because uh we realized that in
some instan it's nice to have a central
compute instance where people all log in
and they all work on the same data this
is fantastic for uh open data sets this
is fantastic if people are actually all
on the same institution and they all
collaborate on an Institutional server
and that's really useful and used a lot
also for teaching obviously that's a
really great setup because teachers can
then log into the other uh students noes
and quickly have a look what's happening
there if they struggle if they have a
problem but then we also have this
Federated model where every in let's say
researchers are collaborating from
different institutions they just install
it on their infrastructure on their
computer and they run analysis on their
data and then they can for example
aggregate high level results in a
publication uh without sharing actually
any confidential data so let's say brain
extraction or brain uh let's say
cortical thickness measurements right so
you could easily share those without
actually exposing the patient data
that's underlying this and then then
that can be shared across different
institutions so that's a really cool
model as well that we see often used
with our our
project and with this I claim that we
made maintaining and installing
scientific software fun again so it's
now very easy uh basically you install
neur desk on these different systems and
we make sure that the software runs on
these systems so even very recently we
managed to get our containers running on
an MRI scanner so this is a uh Works
particularly well for the seens
ecosystem so seens has a software
platform called open Recon so we can
actually build a software container that
can directly be integrated into a
reconstruction running on the system and
um that is really closing the loop so
now you could yeah acquire data build a
CO model and then deploy it on an analiz
scanner where patients can directly uh
be scanned and the results end up in the
pack system for people uh to look at so
that's really uh great progress with the
last months that we've made
there so I want to quickly show the open
data workflow in neurodes so this is
something that we always focus on a lot
we want to make consuming and producing
open data a lot easier and what we've
built there over the last years is that
they support a lot of tools and
databases that make that possible so
I'll start with importing data so
usually if you produce open data you
would start from for example an MRI
scanner or an EG system or you would
download data from for example open Euro
or the open science framework and then
we have a tool in there that's called
data that can handle a lot of these uh
cases where we can download data from
these systems also xnet we support which
is a a tool commonly used in the Neuro
Imaging space to Archive data and then
we of course support any cloud provider
or any local connections so pretty much
anything this is not an not a complete
list this is just a couple of examples
what we support and then once the data
is in the system we can process the data
using pretty much any software out there
if the data if the software is not yet
there it can easily be added we
currently have more than 100 pieces of
software in there that that the
community wanted and then we can
organize the data and we can document
our analysis so for this we highly work
with the bit standard with the brain
Imaging data structure but also bits has
been extended to the EG world so we
support this as well we support Jupiter
as I said as a way of documenting this
data but you can use also your own
script system whatever you're used to
you can install that um and then we
wanted to make it very easy to share
data with the community so we support
Google collab for example so you can
write your analysis in Jupiter and then
you can provide for example a Google
collab notebook with your paper where
all the analysis run and we stream
software into Google collab so with this
we can even run software that wouldn't
be able to run in Google collab so for
example because you couldn't install it
because Google collab doesn't have
enough disk space for example to install
a certain piece of software and we can
actually run the software in Google
collabs through our streaming
service but also we made sure that we
can easily upload data back to open Euro
again through data lab or we can share
data out to OSF or that we can share our
analysis quickly on GitHub and then
people can start again from this and can
use our data that we produced or our our
derivatives that we produced and then
start the cycle again and then really
yeah enrich the open ecosystem out
there so people often ask what is our
sustainability model uh will it be
around in the next couple of years and
of course that's a very good question
because if you start adopting a
framework like this you invest time in
learning it and you want to be sure that
it's around so we try our best there uh
so we as I said we have been funded
through an a platform Grant in the past
we're currently funded by the mar and
Chan Zuckerberg Foundation through
welcome trust and we're applying for uh
grants left and right to keep the system
growing and developing but of course
Grand funding is very competitive and of
course Brands always want to fund things
that are new they don't want to fund
things in maintenance mode so that is
definitely uh something that we
anticipate so that's why we really want
to build the community so we already
have 10 more than 10 active contributors
we have a lot of the infrastructure
hosted through the community Through the
open science grid uh the egi foundation
where we don't have basically Cloud
bills for us which keeps our costs very
low which is good and also if we have
help us from the community we can also
lower our costs because we don't have to
do certain
work and then we provide neurodes as a
service as well so this goes through a
non-for-profit um Foundation which is
called the Queensland cyber
infrastructure structure foundation and
what they do is they provide neurodes at
a certain cost for for example a
conference for a workshop or for
University so let's say you don't want
to use the open source software and do
everything yourself you can go to qf and
say I want this professionally managed I
want a service contract I want an SLA
I'm happy to pay money for that and I
don't I want to use cloud resources for
example and then cus can can provision
that and set it up in a way that it's uh
really at scale and working really well
with with certain guarantees as well um
and then this money flows back to us to
develop things further and then we also
have a lot of support from cloud
providers so as I said we heavily run
Cloud Technologies so we had been
supported by Oracle cloud in the
beginning then Google cloud and now
currently our main sponsor there is AWS
and the research clouds like egi
Jetstream aadc which support us with
Cloud resources and make us all
possible so I want to quickly show you
some results from this reproducibility
aspect because I'm always claiming that
neurodes is reproducible but is it and
how reproducible is it so this is
something that we looked at so PhD
student in my group took that original
paper that I showed earlier from Tristan
clar where they found these
reproducability issues with software so
we took that paper and thought um tested
can we reproduce the non-reproducibility
of software so the analysis is the
following uh we picked this part where
we have data was scanned from an MRI
scanner in anatomical space what they
have to do is we have to register it to
the m& space so this means we align it
to a template space which FSL with which
a with a tool called FSL flirt and then
we take this data and we segment it so
we segment subcortical areas and we uh
measure for example the size of that so
it's a very simple pipeline where you
think that should be pretty easy to
reproduce so what we did is we used a
very similar setup than what clar used
in their paper where we have a local
installation of FSL so FSL is the same
but then once we run on gipc versions
231 so on a Ubuntu 2004 at the neurodes
we chose a quite old version of yuntu uh
with the quite old version of GPC but
the cool thing is the GPC version is
consistent whereas here the GPC version
is 2.28 so something in the middle it's
on Alma Linux 8.5 and then also what we
varied is weent varied the processor so
here it's an an i7 and here it's an AMD
appic processor so let's see what
happens so we of course we compare these
different systems now let's see what
happens so the first thing is image
intensity differences so the first thing
is we were able to replicate the
problems from the paper so if you have a
local installation with two different
gipc versions then you get different
results and this is really intensity so
we we only focus on the intensity in the
area where we will later do an analysis
so this actually the intensity change as
whole brain but just to show where the
problems are so we basically see that
the the intensity of a boxel is like up
to
one one integer value different
and this is small because when you think
about the images are usually like 0 to
1,24 so a change of one doesn't matter
much but still it's a change and it
shouldn't be there so the cool thing is
when we run this a neurodes where we
control gipc the gipc version this
effect is not there there's nothing
there and that's exactly how it should
look like there shouldn't be a
difference between this it's a fully um
deterministic analysis there shouldn't
be any variance between that and that's
cool so then when we look at the
classification differences so this is
now when we segment this data um we see
again in the local installation with
different GPC versions we see quite High
disagreements between labels and this is
now dice score so this is between zero
and one and a016 dice score is quite a
lot when you think about it um so this
means we actually disagree in certain
areas quite a lot between segmentation
and again that shouldn't be the case now
in neurodes you still see something
there however note that the scale is an
order of magnitude scale down so we had
to scale it down to make anything
visible there but we wanted to show it
and why is that why is neurodes here
showing some non-reproducibility because
I just claimed that we are reproducible
right and why are we suddenly not and we
looked into this so we looked we traced
the executions of this program um and we
found that as expected in the local
installation the software diverges so
we're doing different things on
different computers with different GPC
versions and that's why we're getting
different results so that explains it
it's great on neurodes we're not
diverging we're doing exactly the same
thing on both computers so this means on
a software level it's reproducible but
why is there still a different result
and the reason is that we use different
processors was an Intel processor one
was an epic AMD epic processor so
different instruction sets different
floating Point positions can still have
an effect that we cannot control for
even if we do everything the same we get
still small differences they're tiny but
they're still there so it's something to
to note that 100% reproducibility will
only be possible if you also control the
hardware but then in the end you have to
yeah have a trade-off there right when
when is when is reproducibility enough
uh and when how much effort do you want
to put into having reproducible results
there so yeah that's just uh our results
there so a little bit of an Outlook what
we're working on next so there's a lot
of things we do work on but one thing
that I really want to see live in the
next years is interactive papers because
that's what we can do now we can have an
analysis in a jupyter notebook where we
describe what we've done we can show all
the results we can show all the analysis
we could run everything and everyone
could rerun it as well and then base
their analysis on it and Fork papers and
really say well my analysis based on
that paper and have open data for pretty
much everything and really uh yeah make
it easy to to contribute to this open
Science World and we already see some
adoptions from this from from bigger
journals like e life they already have
like some of these executable papers so
seeing this coming through there's still
quite a bit of work required to make
this easy and and very doable but uh our
nees paper for example we already did
that so the neur paper you can go and
reproduce it and you can reproduce our
reproducibility analysis for example
which we thought was quite
nice so with this I'm at the end uh of
my talk so I just want to highlight that
um it's an open community so if you uh
we we need we need Community we need
Community engagement so if you like what
we've done if it's useful for you get in
touch help us build new things find bugs
and um yeah we also have a little bit of
time still left to show neurodes
connection if this is something you want
to see go to our website um neurod des.
org click on hosted and then you see we
have different services and I'll said we
choose the place service with different
regions Australia us and Europe so if
you're roughly in one of these regions
pick that one so I said I'll pick
Australia I just want to uh quickly
highlight here that all of these servers
require some kind of a login Australia
you need to be an Australian researcher
because that's how the service is funded
in the US and Europe you need to have a
GitHub login at least um so I'll click
Australia then what happens is we'll
authenticate you with an account in case
of Australia we use an Australian access
account in then you just say Okay I want
a default environment there shouldn't be
anything else available for you this
will start up uh a Jupiter Notebook on
cloud resources um that are in that
country so you don't want to put patient
data there of course but you can put uh
open data there and in terms of storage
uh you have a home directory which has
about 2 gigaby of storage you will get a
warning if it's full and then nothing
will work anymore so you need to be care
that this is not happening and then
everything else you change on the system
will be reset after after your session
is done but that's basically how it
looks like you go into this system and
then it's just a very familiar Jupiter
notebook system so I quickly want to
show
now um we have for example an example
repository which I quickly want to show
so I'll just I'll just show it on the
website first so what we've done is we
build an example repository of lots of
different workflows where uh we for
example show how to use pipeline systems
on here we show how to do diffusion
analysis for
MRI uh lots of lots of different things
and we're currently building that out so
if you have a tool that you want in
there please go and contribute an
example contribute a tool and what we
can also do is I can I can easily take
this and also run this on our website so
for this uh we will just just check out
this
repository so I'll just show that um so
just clone our example
notebooks and
then that will take a
couple yep so here our example
notebooks and then we can just pick an
example here so I'll pick structural
Imaging and then I'll take the
uh I'll take the functional Imaging
where is it intro to pre-processing I
just wanted to have a very quick one to
show yeah okay so night pipe short so
that's a really quick one to show so um
what we do is we have a first cell where
we set up neurodes this is not needed if
you run this in a neurodes environment
but it's needed outside for example in
Google collab and then we output which
CPU are running on Just for reputability
reasons and then you can import any
software into this notebook so for
example here I install I import FSL and
this is a software that we provide so
this software will now get string into
this notebook and then we can run any
tool from the software you can also
install any python libraries anything um
you need but yeah that was uh really the
the streaming that you saw so that this
B tool was now streamed into this
notebook and now can be used in anything
and this the same way we can load pretty
much any software and have it also
documented what software we're using in
which version we're using it and then
I'll just uh download some test data and
and show that so I'll quickly run this
note book um while this is running I
want to show something else because
notebooks are great but sometimes it
just needs more it needs a desktop and
this is what we can do so we can launch
a full virtual desktop in the system
which should look familiar if you've
used the Linux desktop before but
ultimately uh it has a little start
button down here where you go into NE
desk menu and you see we have lots of
different categories right now for
functional Imaging electrophysiology
diffusion Imaging and then you can start
pretty much anything from here with
visualization software and you can just
start the software it should start it
should run and should behave exactly as
what you're used to as I said the first
startup will always be a little bit
slower um because it has to stream the
software but then you you can browse
brain Imaging data and access everything
you
want so now I want to show quickly as
well
um one more one more way of of using
that so I said earlier we have this this
jup notebook so I can also open this in
Google
collab so when I open this in Google
collab I'll just do the same thing here
run
all this is now really cool because this
is what I mentioned like this you could
attach to your paper where you have your
whole analysis coded up in there and
then run it on on Google collab and it
will be behave identically than what you
just built on the neur desk instance for
example um while this is
running
um see yeah I'll keep this running I
just want to show one more way of doing
it so uh oh yeah okay but that will not
work currently just sharing the screen
because I only share the browser but yes
so then there's ways of how you can run
it locally on your computer uh with a
Docker container so you only need Docker
installed it can run on high performance
Computing clusters pretty much anywhere
where you should need it it should run
um and when I just go back to our
website
quickly um yeah your high performance
Computing system we have instructions
here how to do this even if you don't
want this whole setup around we have
ways of just installing a single
container and you can use that in Docker
or in Singularity so it's really a a
very layered approach of this whole
system so if you just want everything
and no work then just take the top
hosted versions and then you can just go
down the technology stack and use what
you need for your work that's really uh
what we've built and let's see if that
now finished by now so this this will
still take some time
um let's
see I'll see if this one is finished by
now um yeah so basically now this Rand
analysis it downloaded data and then
maybe I can show that one
see uh we also have built in
visualizations which is quite nice so we
can in a jupter notebook this is using a
library called miew where we can browse
uh and visualize neuroimaging data so
yeah so the notebook is still running so
that's why it's not executing it yet but
yeah once it's once it's getting there
it will um
so yeah that's really that's really what
we've built so yeah um while this
running we can we can take some
questions uh Bradley if you have
anything that people might want to ask
um I can show that well wait but
otherwise that's pretty much what I had
prepared yeah that sounds good thank you
um I'm a little I'm interested in the
containerization aspect of this so this
is you know something that you can run
kind of on any machine
on any kind of computing um Paradigm
like you know if you want to run on the
cloud or on your laptop corre so a lot
of the people in the group you know
they're interested in active inference
they're interested in sort of building
their own tools and then how maybe to do
containerization as part of that
strategy yes so can you speak to that a
little bit yeah exactly exactly so if
you build your own tools um you can just
basically build them in here just get
them to work first and then once they
work I'll quickly show how this would
look like then um when you want to
containerize it um so for example let's
say it's a it's a python tool or a mlab
tool mlab we have to compile and then we
download it I'll just uh I can show that
quickly so for example SPM as an example
there so SPM is a brain uh brain imaging
software as well and if you're ready to
containerize it you can send us this
build.sh file where you basically build
a container uh based on a certain Ubuntu
version and you set everything up
yourself and here's an example where we
download a compiled zip file for mlab
that then runs in a mlab runtime
environment and we have lots of tricks
to make this recipe quickly quickly
writable so this is actually a higher
level language which is called which is
developed by neuro Docker team and this
higher level language makes easy to
build containers because if you if you
want to build containers yourself
there's actually a lot of optimization
that has to go into it and with this
higher level abstraction makes it easier
to to build these containers but then
yeah once you have a software it's
pretty easy to run it in here and even
if you don't want to containerize it if
you got it to work in here and you have
the steps to do it it will run on any
neurodes system pretty much so that's
the uh that's the cool thing so if you
have a python library and it's just
three steps to install it you can do
that as well you don't have to
containerize it only if you really want
to freeze it in time make it really um
robust across different systems then
this is the way to go yeah so does this
make sense yes yes and then I I would
like to ask you know what does the
future look like I mean do you have a
road map where you're going out five
years or so and and if so what are the
needs that you need to kind of address
in that road map yeah exactly so yes we
have lots of ideas how to how to go
forward with this it always will depend
on funding what we can do in terms of
new features one thing we do want is and
we're heavily working on this right now
is getting into the clinical space more
to make it very easy to run the software
anywhere so currently we're still need
needing some containerization like
Docker podman Singularity obtainer we
want to and we we just have a prototype
for that where we actually bring
everything we need like we use a quo
based emulation or
virtualization and if the virtualization
framework is enabled on a computer it's
not even emulated so it's really native
speed and with this we can run anywhere
on any system really and we have no
limitations anymore currently you still
need some privileges to start a
container on a system and this is really
needed for these clinical um scenarios
where we want to get into so this is one
thing we're building out running these
containers on an MRI scanner that will
be a lot of work in the next months and
then uh the other thing is lots of other
communities have contacted us so this is
now focused on brain Imaging right but
active inference might have lots of
different tools there and they might
want to build their own flavor of this
like an active inference neurodes and we
have communities like the genomics
community microscopy uh Dermatology they
want to do this as well so what we will
be doing is we will refactor everything
that's not neuroimaging and put that
into a new project and then we have
spin-off projects like neurodes that use
this underlying technology but then they
build the software around it and then
Community maintains that one um and
builds their own flavor of this this is
something we're going to do in the next
years um we still need some funding to
accomplish that but I'm thinking that is
yeah that is absolutely needed to
support other communities there and
there's also a whole underlying thing of
what cloud technology we're using right
so all of these things don't have to be
reinvented if another Community wants to
use that so that's that's really our
road map for the next years making that
yeah more General and yeah and specific
at same time like more clinical as well
yeah well thank you yeah it's
good cool okay um yeah not sure so I
know some visitations came through so I
can quickly show that so this is
something which is I think really
valuable for a lot of brain Imaging
people so you can just quickly yeah look
at the brain which is really cool in in
Ain browser so you don't need any fancy
software there and yeah that's what for
example in this case new makes possible
and I think this is really our our
fundamental um philosophy with this
right we want to just bring the right
tools to the right people and make it
easy to use them so they can do awesome
work that's really what our project is
about yeah thank you very much and
wonderful people if people have
questions after this talk shoot me an
email um and contact us through GitHub
or gith have discussion forums and we're
happy to help thank you right thank you
yeah all right that's all we have for
that um I don't know if we have any
questions we want to ask I can try to
answer them okay if people have any
questions in the live chat they can add
but thanks for sharing this and for
bringing this important flavor into the
mix
um where it took me was right where you
asked at the end with stripping back to
the desk and then allowing the spin-offs
and thinking about how we could use that
and just how it's like the through line
of the education the research the
application that's kind of tracing back
the community and information supply
chain to Applications of activ inference
so when we come to a symposium like this
or think about planning a symposium like
this think about making a startup or
something like that using this in an
application setting and we trace it back
and then that's where these topics like
reproducibility and research Integrity
are the foundations of the
application and if there's ambiguity in
all these different threads and loose
ends like from the availability of the
papers things that have been focused on
in
science across fields and then these
really specific
computational
issues and then the example with a
versioning of a
library having these cascading
consequences to say nothing of like
security issues it's just
completely it's like an
empirical open science point that was
very well made and so now where do we go
from that
observation right right yeah I mean i'
I've had experience with
containerization um you know in the
openworm foundation which I also work
with uh they they've developed a
container for demos and they run their
simulations in a series of demos and the
idea is to be able to get people to use
the demo and get everything to run you
don't need any dependencies on your
machine you just worry about running the
the container and that's it and it's
been successful I mean it's a little
tricky to use and get to work but you
know the idea is to make things
reproducible so if you see something in
a paper or see something that I show you
a demo of you can reproduce it for
yourself and it's everything's the same
so you get the same answer and you can
even maybe like modify some of the
variables or parameters in that model
and see you know work with it on your
own and know that that's
uh you know that what you're seeing is
actual an actual result not just some
noise or difference that comes from the
computational
environment yeah um like practically
what are some interesting ways that as
we digest all of this year and think
about what projects
like as a scientific Advisory board or
just as an Institute or as part of
coalitions
what would be interesting how how do you
how do you see that popping up across
these different research
communities yeah I think well for one
you could use some of the packages that
we've seen in the Symposium you could
run them in a container and it would
help people if you're running them in
different locations like if you're in a
research group or if you're in a uh just
a casual you know learner who's trying
to run an analysis it would equalize the
ability to run those tools but also you
know we can develop demos um if people
are interested where you show you
demonstrate active inference and you put
it in a container so someone might run a
contain you know someone who is learning
about active inference could run a
container and they could run these
simulations and they'd be you know able
to run them no matter where they are and
it doesn't take them a lot of effort to
sort of install dependencies cuz
sometimes and when you want to say
demonstrate something in a simulation
you need to have people run like you
know a bunch of things on top of one
another and not everyone can either do
that or can run them on their own
machine successfully so that hinders
what we can do in terms of demonstration
and Education and Research so that just
takes care of that layer and then
everything else is like you can worry
about like doing the good stuff doing
the demos doing the science
as you've had many years of working in
open source like what heris discs or
intuitions do we have in our toolkit
when again just cuz something could be
open source doesn't mean it necessarily
should so how do we add
signal not noise or Worse how do we
navigate between getting overwhelmed
with the technical complexity of trying
to take on all of these new research
practices and and just
like we we could spend all all of our
computer time making something
reproducible I I I I I don't know
exactly where I'm going with that but
just how do we guide and just put out
especially if we're putting out
capacities related to cognitive modeling
perception
control then is there any kinds of
considerations that we should think
about before just releasing really
effective containers for
that yeah so I mean I guess what's in a
container is basically the software that
you release as open source and of course
there has to be a strategy for releasing
open source software you just don't dump
software out on the web or you just
don't like kind of produce a bunch of
files and then you know with limited
documentation until people have at it
every group has their own strategy and a
lot of that is you know to think about
the utility of what you're releasing as
an open source package so sometimes
you're interested in the uh commercial
value sometimes they proprietary value
in releasing something or not sometimes
you release you have code but it's not
well documented so the utility there is
limited and that people can't reuse it
so that doesn't necessarily make it good
to
release um you know so you want to be
able to have I think and I I say this as
being a full supporter of Open Source
activity but to release things that are
very Polished in the sense that you know
why you want to release it and you have
the right support in place and sometimes
groups will have the resources to do
that and sometimes they won't so if
you're a small academic lab then you
don't really you can't spend a lot of
time you know polishing the software uh
in the talk I I gave early I think it
was yesterday I talked about like kind
of these practices of software
engineering and that sort of thing and
that's something that not every group
can do so that means that we maybe need
either organizations to kind of have
that layer of you know uh making things
work well before release them or having
meta organizations that can help
scientific organizations do these kind
of releases and I'm against like making
something open source for like a paper
I'm just saying that like in tool
building you know you have to have a
deliberate strategy for it and it's it
it pays off if you
do yeah that's very wise like your talk
in part one and seeing this again and um
the prior talk on NGC learn and the
Museum of examples and going Beyond just
curating links to to hosting more and
more and that is what will allow
Learners to have access to these tools
build their intuition about the topic
maybe continue on and kind of um
converge into the development attractor
but even
finding friction points and bugs and
Reporting it and just putting up a
yellow flag or just asking it the
question a lot of times it feels like
people who are outside of the
development don't realize that
those visibilities that and experiences
that they have into
the
outcome can be in the blind spots or
just forgotten by by bandwidth
constrained
developers and then that is like our
research Community with people who are
at different stages and using tools
differently so it's like how could we
not have this yet it's hard to to hold
that yeah and it is it it is a Commons
for for
computational
science which wasn't really part of the
pre- internet
pre-computer research world and so
there's all these forms and functions
that we barely barely even able to
describe let alone what has really been
tried in different epistemic
niches so it's it's super exciting
because there's so much experimentation
across multiple scales people doing
things on their own being their own
program manager on through just with
friends working with AI and the kinds of
things people are asking and the
artifacts they're getting to and then
even up to like the metago type
coordinations of organizations who want
to
have Commons and be particular but also
find the
interfaces that will help them do things
together they can't do
separately
yeah
um do you have any sort of last thoughts
or question questions and what would be
some exciting directions for you and or
The Institute in the year to
come yeah so I mean uh Daniel asked me
to contribute something on this topic
and and kind of in the abstract because
we do it looks like we do a lot of open
source and and things and it's just kind
of you know to develop a strategy there
to develop a vision there as the thing
that we want to get to so um you know I
would say that like
um you know one thing might be and I
think this is very useful is to have a
sort of educational component where you
can have some you know tools for active
inference and to teach people sort of
how to you you know we we usually use
simulations as an educational tool and
making simulations are you know a nice
tool because you people can interact
with them and so you know and it doesn't
have to be like a very highle simulation
be a very simple thing that
demonstrations of things demonstrations
of Concepts where we might package uh
some sample data with a sample
simulation and say here build your own
sort of active inference model and you
know kind of walk people through how to
do it and then eventually they'll start
playing with it and they'll say oh this
is great and I want to get in more into
some of these topics and then that's
that's sort of a Gateway into the
institute for people who may not feel
comfortable with a lot of you know kind
of diving right into the technical
jargon they want to have like a a nice
sort of way to ease in and and something
that's intuitive and then that helps
them um but other things you know like
like as Stefan said you know that kind
of the thing that they're working on
neurodes is for Neuro Imaging but you
can use different versions of this for
you know different sorts of things and
there're also different versions of
Linux that you can build like your own
custom version of so uh in the talk that
I gave earlier there's uh neurod Debian
which has the ability to build these
builds where you build them as like a
specialized operating system for a
certain thing they have neurod Debian
which is for Neuroscience but there can
be other versions of Debian for like you
know musicians or data scientists and
maybe you know I don't know if it's
useful but but to have something for
active inference with all the tools
included and you just you know download
that that re that drro and you get the
tools and they they
work thank you these are all great
directions a closing note I think it'd
be very appropriate in a history Rhymes
kind of way that the more generalized
cybernetics arose out of neuroimaging
and we saw SPM package in one of the
presentations and then also
neuroimaging and the special constraints
like computational resources patient
privacy those constraints in that
community of
neuroimaging also leading the way on the
tooling which we can also learn from
with more General
systems yeah yeah okay thank you for
this all right see you thank you